Finding Aid for Valde Garcia Papers, 1999-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Valde Garcia papers 1999-2010
Garcia, Valde.
2011008 Aa 2
Michigan Republican State Senator; the collection relates primarily to proposed legislation, other files document issues of concern to the Hispanic community of Michigan; also issues relating to Michigan veterans.
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Valde Garcia (donor no. 10465 ) and came to the library in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Valde Garcia was born November 27, 1958. He grew up in Clinton county but came to reside in Howell (in Livingston county). He graduated from Cedarville College, Cedarville, OH, with a bachelor's degree in political science. Sometime after graduation he enlisted in the United States Army. He was on active duty for nine years, being honorably discharged in 1990. As a member of Army Reserve, Garcia was recalled to active duty in 1991 for Operation Desert Storm. Here he served as commander of an infantry training company at Fort Benning, GA. When his tour of duty was completed and before seeking election on his own, Garcia worked as chief of staff and legislative aid for different state senators. He also taught at Laingsburg Christian School and was territory manager for the National Federation of Independent Business.
Valde Garcia was elected the Michigan House of Representatives in 1998 and the Michigan Senate in 2001 where he was the first Hispanic state senator for the state of Michigan. Representing the 22nd district of Michigan (comprised of Livingston, Shiawassee, and the southern part of Ingham counties) Garcia served from 2001 to 2010. While in the Senate, Garcia was a member of various committees, including Appropriations, Senior Citizens and Veterans Affairs, and Homeland Security and Emerging Technologies.
The Papers of Valde Garcia contains documents that span his entire career as a Michigan State Senator from 2001 to 2010. A small number of records date from Garcia's time as a Michigan State Representative before entering the senate. The collection is arranged into three series: Bills and Legislation, Hispanic Issues, and Personal Records.
Subjects:
Garcia, Valde.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislative. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.; Republican Party (Mich.); Veterans--United States.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.
- Bills and Legislation
  The Bills and Legislation series (9.5 linear feet) includes bills, resolutions, requests, correspondence and other related materials from 2001 to 2010. The bills are numbered in chronological order.
  - Legislative Session 2001-2002
    - SB 503 -- Deferred Presentment Services (Box 1)
    - Bill Request #4489'01 -- Deceased Parents Retirement to Children (Box 1)
    - Bill Request #5923'01 -- Zero-Tolerance for Domestic Violence in Subsidized Housing (Box 1)
    - Bill Request #6170'01 -- Translators for State Agencies and Courts (Box 1)
    - Senate Resolutions 144 and 263, 60th Anniversary of Pearl Harbor, Hispanic Heritage Month (Box 1)
  - Legislative Session 2003-2004
    - SB 27 -- Active Military Duty Healthcare Pay (Box 1)
    - SB 28 -- Rank for Adjutant General (Box 1)
    - SB 112 -- Choose Life License Plates (Box 1)
    - SB 113 -- Non-profit Fee (Box 1)
    - SB 114 -- Limited Liability Company Fee (Box 1)
    - SB 115 -- The Revised School Code/Access to Schools (Box 1)
    - SB 167 -- Profit Corporation Fees (Box 1)
    - SB 171 -- Recreational Authorities (Box 1)
    - SB 342 -- Fire System Tax Exemption (Box 1)
    - SB 466 -- Michigan Vehicle Code/Choose Life License Plates (Box 1)
    - SB 474 -- Deferred Presentment, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - SB 484 -- Teacher Tax Credit, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - SB 528 -- Apology as Evidence in Trial, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - SB 529 -- Lottery Commission CAP (Box 2)
    - SB 542 and 543 -- Animal Testing, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - SB 590 -- Lottery License Fees (Box 2)
    - SB 764 -- Fetal Guardianship (Box 2)
    - SB 786 -- Anhydrous Ammonia Regulation (Box 2)
    - SB 884 -- Credit Scoring (Box 2)
    - SB 951 -- Active Military Duty Arrest Powers (Box 2)
    - SB 965 -- Interests of Childs (Box 2)
    - SB 1138-Michigan Occupational Safety and Health Act "MIOSHA", Credit Toward Fines (Box 2)
    - SB 1269 and 1270 -- Military Family Relief Fund (Box 2)
    - SB 1286 -- Survivor Benefits Tax (Box 2)
    - SB 1364 -- Sexually Explicit Videos in Cars (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #0241'03 -- Honorarium Ban for Elected Officials (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #0390'03 -- Reading Pilot Project (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1309'03 -- Michigan Community Economic Development Fund (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1324'03 -- Military/Active Service Employer (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1326'03 -- School Recess Bill (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1327'03 -- Teacher Contract (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1328'03 -- Medical Profession Loan Defaulters (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1336'03 -- Estates and Protected Individuals Code (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1337'03 -- Flag Display (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1338'03 -- Criminal Actions to Certain Civil Infractions (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1339'03 -- Trampoline Insurance (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1340'03 -- American Gaming Fund (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1343'03 -- Migratory Labor Housing Licensing and Grants Act (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1348'03 -- Auto Glass Repair (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #1349'03 -- Mexican Driver's Licenses (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #2399'03 -- School Days (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #2957'03 -- Newspaper "Deposit" (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #2995'03 -- Identity Theft (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #3363'03 -- Grandparents Rights/Military Service (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #3858'03 -- Video Voyeurism (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #3955'03 -- Special Assessment Definition In Revenue Sharing Act (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #4153'03 -- License Plate Re-Issue (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #4186'03 -- Custody Changes; Establish Timeline (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #5928'03 -- Income Tax Rollback (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #6219'04 -- Hearing Impaired Child in Area Speed Limit (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #6403'04 -- LDFA (incompatible public officers) (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #7724'04 -- Vietnam Veterans Memorial Land (Box 2)
    - Bill Request #7777'04-Deferred Presentment (Box 2)
    - Mobile Homes Bills 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Mobile Homes Supplementary Materials, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Mobile Home Issues (Box 3)
    - Senate Bills --Unknown Number or Status (Box 3)
    - Senate Resolutions, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Other Materials Related to Legislative Session
      - Boy/Girl Scout License Plates, Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Epinephrine Right-to-Carry (Box 3)
      - Immigrant ID Cards (Box 3)
      - Insurance Steering (Box 3)
      - Local Approval of Sewage Construction (Box 3)
      - Manufactured Housing List 2004, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Mexican Driver's Licenses (Box 4)
      - Migrant Services Streamlining and Consolidation (Box 4)
      - Motorcycle Education Courses (Box 4)
      - Occupancy Assessment for Property Tax (Box 4)
      - Paternity Suit Standing (Box 4)
      - Suicide Awareness Curriculum (Box 4)
      - Supplemental Dealer Licenses (Motor Homes) (Box 4)
  - Legislative Session 2005-2006
    - SB 93 -- Character Education (Box 4)
    - SB 94 -- Suicide Awareness (Box 4)
    - SB 95 -- School Hours (Box 4)
    - SB 96 -- Coach's Code-of-Conduct (Box 4)
    - SB 97 -- Argo/Off-Road Recreational Vehicles (Box 4)
    - SB 99 -- Fire Autopsy (Box 4)
    - SB 100 -- School Zoning (Box 4)
    - SB 101 -- Cancer Presumption (Box 4)
    - SB 182 -- Clinical Lab Science (Box 4)
    - SB 194 -- Coast Guard Commemoration (Box 4)
    - SB 195 --Agricultural Labor Camp (Box 4)
    - SB 231 -- Radiation Imaging (Box 4)
    - SB 287 -- Employee Retirement (Box 5)
    - SB 299-Foundation Allowance Increase (Box 5)
    - SB 359 -- Biosciences and Commercialization Center (Box 5)
    - SB 366 -- Shooting Range Hours, Bill Request (Box 5)
    - SB 405 -- Construction Lien Fund, Bill Request (Box 5)
    - SB 424 -- Transportation Bonds Approval (Box 5)
    - SB 454 -- Non-profit Embezzlement (Box 5)
    - SB 455 -- Sentencing Guidelines Non-Profit Embezzlement (Box 5)
    - SB 469-Earned Income Tax Credit (Box 5)
    - SB 474 -- Repeal Treasury Advisory Board (Box 5)
    - SB 495 -- Electronic Waste (Box 5)
    - SB 533-$1 Billion Bond (Box 5)
    - SB 596 -- Health Insurance Tax Credit (Box 5)
    - SB 727 -- Michigan Strategic Fund (Box 5)
    - SB 805 -- Used Car Dealer License (Box 5)
    - SB 809 -- Disability Registration (S.U.V) (Box 5)
    - SB 877 -- Anhydrous Ammonia Security (Box 6)
    - SB 878-Anhydrous Ammonia Tax Credit (Box 6)
    - SB 906 -- Chief Compliance Officer (Job Package) (Box 6)
    - SB 934 -- Selective Service via SOS, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Selective Service System -- Supplementary Materials (Box 6)
    - SB 1110 -- Child Abuse Probation Increase (Box 6)
    - SB 1128 -- Military Child Support Modification (Box 6)
    - SB 1140 -- Fire Marshall Transfer (Box 6)
    - SB 1144 -- Fire Fighter Civil Immunity (Box 6)
    - SB 1287 -- Expand Exemptions for Incompatible Public Offices of Higher Education Institutions (Box 6)
    - SB 1288 -- MI Works (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #366'05 -- Legislator Active Duty (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #369'05 Minimum Wage Exemptions (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #3093'05 -- Disabled and Unemployed Business Tax Credits (Box 6)
    - Bill Requests #3995'05 -- Disabled and Unemployed Business Tax Credits (Box 6)
    - Bill Requests #3996'05 -- Personal Property Tax Reform (Box 6)
    - Bill Requests #3997'05 -- Medicaid Overpayment Statute of Liberties (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4103'05 -- Defense and Homeland Security Bond Fund (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4260'05 -- Sales Tax Reform (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4261'05 -- Use Tax Reform (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4805'05 -- Police Canine Vet (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4805a'05 (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #4808'05 (Box 6)
    - Bill Request #6740'06 -- License Mortgage Loan Officers (Box 6)
    - Bill Request -- Military Family Leave Act (Box 6)
    - Senate Bills -- Unknown Number or Status (Box 6)
    - Senate Joint Resolution J -- Legislator Replacement (Box 6)
    - Other Materials Related to Legislative Session
      - MEDC Commercial Development (Box 6)
      - State Minimum Wage (Box 6)
      - Homeland Security (Box 6)
      - LSB Publications (Box 6)
  - Legislative Session 2007-2008
    - SB 100 -- Character Education (Box 7)
    - SB 101 -- Michigan Virtual University (Box 7)
    - SB 102 -- Workman's Comp -- Firefighter (Box 7)
    - SB 103 -- Domestic Violence Rental Termination (Box 7)
    - SB 104 -- Right-of-Way Violations (Box 7)
    - SB 105 -- Magistrates Arraignments (Box 7)
    - SB 106 -- Meritorious Defense for Malpractice Lawsuits (Box 7)
    - SB 179 -- School Retirement (Box 7)
    - SB 180 -- School Retirement Purchase (Box 7)
    - SB 181 -- Disability Registration (SUV) (Box 7)
    - SB 266 -- Household Movers (Box 7)
    - SB 267 -- Auto Dealers (Box 7)
    - SB 345 -- Industrial Facilities Exemption Certificate (Box 7)
    - SB 349 -- Tax Credit for Animal Welfare Fund (1) (Box 7)
    - SB 350 -- Tax Credit for Animal Welfare Fund (2) (Box 7)
    - SB 487 -- Construction Lein Fix (Box 7)
    - SB 497 -- State Beef Commission (Box 7)
    - SB 513 -- Tuthill Farm (Box 7)
    - SB 528 -- Daily Rental Property Depreciated Schedule (Box 7)
    - SB 550 -- Intergovernmental Transfer of Functions (1) (Box 7)
    - SB 557 -- Intergovernmental Transfer of Functions (2) (Box 7)
    - SB 573 -- School Employee Compensation (Box 7)
    - SB 580 -- Fire Death Autopsy (Box 7)
    - SB 599 -- Canine Unit Reimbursement (Box 7)
    - SB 606 -- Combat Zones/Occupational Code License Renewal Fee (Box 7)
    - SB 635 -- Housing Inspections (Box 8)
    - SB 697 -- Driver's Responsibility Fee Payment (Box 8)
    - SB 698 -- Utility Lines (Box 8)
    - SB 699 -- School Safety Zone (Box 8)
    - SB 719 -- Twins Legislation (Box 8)
    - SB 738-Veterans Tuition Grant Act (Box 8)
    - SB 739 -- State Competitive Scholarships (Box 8)
    - SB 747 -- Parent Deployment/Student Absence (Box 8)
    - SB 753 -- Veteran Road Test Waiver (Box 8)
    - SB 819 -- Military Cell Phone Contracts (Box 8)
    - SB 851 -- Divestment -- MI Strategic Fund (Box 8)
    - SB 852 -- Divestment -- 21st Century Jobs Fund (Box 8)
    - SB 879 -- "Kids Day" (Box 8)
    - SB 897 -- Electronic Waste, Bill Request #2158'07, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - SB 903 -- Landfills -- Electronics (Richardville), Bill Request#1217'07 (Box 8)
    - SB 1068 -- 7 Day Quit Notice (Renters) (Box 8)
    - SB 1162 -- Choose Life License Plates (Box 8)
    - SB 1163 -- Adult Foster Care Facility (Box 8)
    - SB 1171 -- Film Package (Box 8)
    - SB 1201 -- Military Personnel Wireless Contract Act (Box 8)
    - SB 1211 -- Veteran CDL Waiver (Box 8)
    - SB 1251 -- Altering the Commission on Spanish Speaking Affairs (Box 8)
    - SB 1258 -- Regulation of Dangerous Animals, Bill Request (Box 8)
    - SB 1259 -- Dangerous Animals Sentencing Guidelines (Box 8)
    - SB 1260 -- Injured Pets (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #0018'07 -- Classified Information (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2084'07 -- Holding Incompatible Offices Higher Education Institutions (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2085'07 -- Enlarging Forest Trails (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2371'07 -- Gas Tax (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2372'07 -- Michigan-Made Vehicles (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2373'07 -- Sales Tax on Difference between Trade-in and Purchase Price (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2734'07 -- Felon Hire (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2620'07 -- Drug Eviction (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #2997'07 -- Helping Outstanding Pupils Educationally "HOPE" Scholarship (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #3575'07 -- Repeal of State Education Tax Act (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #3645'07 -- DEQ/Fire Bureau Change (1) (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #3645'07a -- DEQ/Fire Bureau Change (2) (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #3700'07 -- "In God We Trust" License Plates (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #3877'07 -- Licensing for Military Speakers (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #4008'07 -- Prisoner Transfers (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #4399'07 -- Preference in Employment (Box 8)
    - Bill Request #4401'07 -- Crime Victims Interstate Agreement (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4409'07 -- Negligent Homicide as Part of Background Check (1) (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4410'07 -- Negligent Homicide as Part of Background Check (2) (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4411'07 -- Negligent Homicide as Part of Background Check (3) (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4600'07 -- DEQ/Fire Bureau Change (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4616'07 -- Negligent Homicide Payment (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #4617'07 -- Sentencing Guidelines for Negligent Homicide and Felonious Driving (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5120'07 -- Barrier Free Laws (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5121'07 -- Barrier Free Laws (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5259'07 -- Shooting Range Abatements (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5260'07 -- Family Military Leave Time (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5261'07 -- Preference in State Employment for Spouses of Disabled Veterans (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5262'07 -- Set Aside Conviction Law (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5263'07 -- Missing Persons Database (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5400'07 -- 1 Cent Sales Tax Increase (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5401'07 -- 2 Cent Sales Tax Increase (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5402'07 -- Income Tax Repeal (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5403'07 -- Use Tax Repeal (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5470'07 -- 21st Century Jobs Fund Increase (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5930'07 -- Rip Tide Safety (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5931'07 -- Military Personal Driving Test Waiver (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #5934'07 -- CCW Licenses for Retired Police (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6201'07 -- Outdoor Wood Burners/Boilers (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6202'07 -- Military License Renewals (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6204'07 -- Power of Attorney (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6205'07 -- Negligent Homicide/Snowmobile (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6330'08 -- Economic Development Fund (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6533'08 -- MI Strategic Fund (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6605'08 -- Negligent Homicide Clean-Up (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6617'08 -- Nondependent Health Care (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #6618'08 -- Unemployment Insurance Agency (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7227'08 -- Nonprofit Fees (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7558'08 -- Firefighter Training-Veterans (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7564'08 -- Shiawassee Distribution Money (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7642'08 -- Senior Citizens Property Tax (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7644'08 -- C.J.I.S LEIN Formula (Box 9)
    - Bill Request #7942'08 -- Amateur Boxing (Box 9)
    - Senate Resolution 80 --US 23 Transit Route, Request #263'07 (Box 9)
    - Senate Resolution 104 -- Insurance Coverage Private/VA Hospitals (Box 9)
    - Senate Resolution 173 -- Month of the Military Child (Box 9)
    - Senate Joint Resolution F -- Replacement Members for Legislature if Called for Active Military Service (Box 9)
    - Senate Joint Resolution G -- Military Tuition Rates (Box 9)
    - Other Materials
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Michigan Department of Environmental Quality (Box 9)
      - Shooting Range Sound Abatement (Box 9)
      - Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago -- Detroit Branch, Money Smart Week (Box 9)
  - Legislative Sessions 2009-2010
    - SB 102 -- FOC Package: Driver's License (Box 10)
    - SB 103 -- FOC Package: Fee Consolidation (Box 10)
    - SB 106 -- Meritorious Defense (Box 10)
    - SB 109 -- Cancer Presumption (Box 10)
    - SB 136 -- Artificial Intelligence Excellence Program (Box 10)
    - SB 137 -- Veterans Benefits: $100 Payment (Box 10)
    - SB 138 -- MI Strategic Fund (Box 10)
    - SB 185 -- Domestic Violence (Box 10)
    - SB 215 -- Commission on Spanish Speaking Affairs (Box 10)
    - SB 371 -- Military Personnel Wireless Contract Act (Box 10)
    - SB 372 -- Hispanic Abortion Reporting (Box 10)
    - SB 545 -- 7 Day Notice to Quit (Box 10)
    - SB 547 -- Construction Lien Act (Box 10)
    - SB 574 -- Veteran CDL Waiver (Box 10)
    - SB 598 -- National Popular Vote (Box 10)
    - SB 633 -- Type 2 Agency (Box 10)
    - SB 717 -- Michigan Information Security Program Standards Act (Box 10)
    - SB 904 -- MI Green Schools (Box 10)
    - SB 1034 -- LEIN Formula Fee (Box 10)
    - SB 1035 -- I-Chat Fee Increase (Box 10)
    - SB 1036 -- Fingerprinting Fee Increase (Box 10)
    - SB 1404 -- Michigan Intelligence Operation Center (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #0028'09 -- Classified Information (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #0033'09 -- Veteran Fire Fighter (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #1879'09 -- Identity Theft Protection (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #2069'09 -- MI Strategic Fund: Mistake (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #2072'09 -- Canine Unit Reimbursement (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #2301'09 -- Prisoner Transfer (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #2459'09 -- Indian Trails (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3039'09 -- Outdoor Wood Burners (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3519'09 -- Veteran Preference Goals (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3581'09 -- Expert Video Testimony (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3040'09 -- MSP Lien Funding/License Plate Fees (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3042'09 -- DMVA Change in Duties (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3792'09 -- Paul White: Auto Dealers (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #3041'09 -- DMVA Certification (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #4257'09 -- Military Electronic Voting (Box 10)
    - Bill Request #6547'10 -- School Bus Advertising (Box 10)
    - Senate Joint Resolution O, Active Military Legislator, #0031'09 (Box 10)
    - Other Materials
      - Michigan Green (Box 10)
      - Michigan Fire Fighters Union -- Public Act 312 (Box 10)
      - Veterans Affairs Budget FY 2009-2010 (Box 10)
      - Statement of John Nelson, Chairman Michigan Veterans Organization Rehabilitation and Veterans Service Committee (Box 10)
      - Veterans Training (Box 10)
- Hispanic Issues
  The Hispanic Issues series (2.5 linear feet) is made up of records related to Garcia’s involvement with the Hispanic community in Michigan. A considerable portion of this series concerns the annual Hispanic Heritage Month Celebration.
  - Agricultural trade opportunities for Michigan produce in Mexico (particularly Michigan apples) 2001 (Box 10)
  - Chavez, Cesar E., Commemoration Events 2005-2009 (Box 10)
  - Commission on Spanish Speaking Affairs (COSSA)
    - Annual report 1996 (Box 10)
    - Brochures: include Michigan's Hispanic Community: A Profile (Box 10)
    - Hispanic Resource Directory 1995, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Meeting materials, correspondence, etc. 1998-2000 (Box 10)
    - Report: Analysis of the Effect of the Governor's Career Scholarship Program on the Hispanic Community 1999 (Box 10)
    - Report: Improving the High Attrition Rate Among Hispanics in the State of Michigan (Box 10)
    - Strategic Plan 2005-2009 (Box 10)
  - Fox (Vicente), President of Mexico, visit to Lansing 2004 (Box 10)
  - Hispanic Contacts (Box 10)
  - Hispanic Heritage Month Celebration
    - 1998-1999 (Box 10)
    - 2000 (Box 10)
    - 2001, 9 folders (Box 11)
    - 2002, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Nominations for Awards 2001-2002, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - 2003 (Box 11)
    - 2004 (Box 11)
    - 2005, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - 2006 (Box 12)
    - 2007, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - 2008 (Box 12)
    - 2009 (Box 12)
  - Hispanic Legislative Conference (First Annual) 1999 (from time as state representative) (Box 12)
  - Immigration Clerical Assistant 2004 (Box 12)
  - Julian Samorra Institute (Box 12)
  - Latino Vote (Box 12)
  - Hispanic Leaders (Box 12)
  - Hispanic Leadership Institute (Box 12)
  - Matricula Consular Identification Card (Box 12)
  - Mexico -- visit of elected officials 2005 (Box 12)
  - Michigan driver's license issued to illegal immigrants (proposed legislation), 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Migrant Labor (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Programs (Box 12)
  - Scholarship Fund 2000 (from time as state representative) (Box 12)
  - Virtual Migrant Education 2000 (from time as state representative) (Box 12)
  - Collected Published material (Box 12)
- Veterans and military issues
  The Veterans and military issues series concerns Garcia’s support and recognition of current members of the military and veterans who had previously served.
  - Flag raising ceremony honoring marines 2004 (Box 13)
  - Memorial Day Services 2002, 2009-2010 (Box 13)
    (includes 2 DVDs of Garcia hosting Services in Senate Chamber)
  - Michigan Veterans Organizations, Rehabilitation and Veterans Service Committee 2007-2008 (Box 13)
  - Military and Veterans Affairs, Dept. of (Box 13)
  - Operation Adopt-A-Family 2003 (Box 13)
  - Patriotic Pillow Project 2005 (Box 13)
  - Phone card press conference 2003 (Box 13)
  - Purple Heart Presentation 1999 (from time as state representative) (Box 13)
  - Tuition (grant in-state tuition for military families) 2008 (Box 13)
  - Veterans Memorial Park Commission 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Veterans (proposed monument on Capitol Square) 2007 (Box 13)
  - Veterans Service Organizations (Box 13)
  - Veterans Miscellaneous (Box 13)
- Other Records
  The Other Records series (0.5 linear feet) contains other items not specifically related to any particular piece of legislation or term in office. This series includes press releases and columns written by Garcia.
  - Correspondence received and sent from Garcia's Office 2000-2005 (includes some records from time as State Representative) (Box 13)
  - Education summit (include Valde's educational legislative accomplishments) (Box 13)